So to get back to Clyde's point,
right,
it's like you had talked initially about like having good looks and then doing this type of like murder,
like what do you see is the correlation between that?
Like given,
you know,
even like we didn't mention the Menendez brothers.
That was a doc that just came out.
Now,
like they're about to be possibly out and things like that.
So what have you found in your research or your studies?
Like,
is there a correlation there?
Or I guess why are people obsessed with good looking people who commit these types of murders?
When I started reading into the story,
I was like,
let me kind of get more of the mental state of like where it all stems from.
When investigating this case,
I learned about the song that she sang in the Maricopa County Jail.
And it's interesting.
It's an amazing voice.
I've showed this video to several people who have openly come out and discuss what it is that they're dealing with when it comes to mental health.
and the issues that they face almost daily.
And every one of those people have said the same thing.
That's the real Jodi Arias in that video.
But it almost feels like a confession when you really listen to the words and even her banter is body language.
It's almost like she's revisiting that night,
that old holy night.
So sitting down and,
you know,
getting to interview and talk with these people,
I learned a lot of inside information that I really don't think became public.
All right,
so with that being said,
welcome back to another episode of the Within Range podcast.
Ear God is on today.
Jared Suter is on today.
Dom Juan.
Guest we have on today is clearly no stranger to the pod.
So,
Clyde,
real quick,
just before we get into this,
listen,
you've been on our show twice now.
We actually interviewed you the first time at a studio in Old Town Scottsdale.
You know,
we've talked to you about UFOs,
aliens before.
Drew,
Jared,
you guys know this.
You're taking us down a different path,
right?
So I guess,
you know,
for people who may have watched our show or keep up with your documentaries,
talk to us about this transition for you and what,
you know,
what's to come with this.
Yeah,
so it's not a complete shift of.
what I'm doing.
I'm still doing the alien stuff,
the unknown,
paranormal,
but the main topic is why is there such a fascination with crime,
murder,
death,
right?
You love this stuff,
so I'm trying to figure out where this all started,
how it happened,
you know what I mean?
We are just in a world where crime is just number one.
Okay,
so listen,
Jared might need to assist me with this,
but it was this lady who was part of this church and I guess somehow it
ended up in a cult setting.
She ended up having an affair,
but her husband got murdered,
and then she and this guy she was having an affair with buried their kids at a farm they had up in Idaho.
But she's been tried here.
I think she was out of Chandler.
It started in Chandler.
I think that's where the church started was in Chandler.
And then,
dude,
it's the biggest case going on in
Arizona right now.
By the end,
I mean,
she was mentally ill,
but she thought she was a god,
and she was getting told.
by God that her kids were demons and that they needed to be killed.
And so they did that.
Buried them.
Yeah.
Found the bodies and everything.
I've been looking into the gentleman up in like Idaho that killed the college students.
You know,
he's on court now.
It's horrifying,
dude.
If I'm not mistaken.
And then another one that I was looking at that,
because you said mental illness,
right?
And that was one of the...
aspects of a lot of the crimes that I was looking at,
even present and past.
The one more that I was focused on was
Luigi Mangione.
The UnitedHealthcare,
right?
Yes.
Yeah.
And it's like,
he didn't,
I mean,
from what I understand,
he went to an...
ivy ivy league school yeah he had a cush life like living good yeah and that type of and and this is all alleged right but if he is the one found that he did this when you look at the video footage and how
he got away and i'm sorry that's not signs of mental illness now um there are other cases out there where you know clearly mental illness is is something that you know can be looked at talked about but that
one right there like that guy
I was that is a pre-planned premeditated yeah and and he executed it with precision you know but another thing that I was looking at is when it comes to the fascination right you said you love crime tv uh what is it if you don't mind me asking what is it about uh
the person that commits the crime who just so happens to to have good looks it's interesting you bring that up because honestly we talked about before this and jared was the one that kind of named off something
killers.
I mean,
Ted Bundy's been known for that.
Luigi Mangione has fans outside of his trial right now.
And like,
listen,
do I think that big insurance companies are something that is like sacred and should be protected and that they're these great people and I can't believe it?
No,
I can see it.
I can see how it happened.
But we can't be glorifying just murdering a man in the streets.
I get the statement.
Other ways to make it,
you know what I mean?
And so these people that are just in there cheering for this guy,
it's just like,
oh.
Imagine seeing your daughter in there like,
oh my God,
Louie.
You're just like,
oh,
jeez.
There is a fascination for,
once again,
crying that just blows my mind.
And that's why this shift is happening,
because it's like really trying to find the starting point.
of it.
And,
you know,
one person that I think of,
outside of like Charles Manson,
he didn't really have the looks.
He had a harem.
You know,
but it was like,
you know,
I think he had like the way with the words.
He had the charisma.
He had the mouthpiece.
And fans,
like you said,
that they just,
even now,
now he still has fans but the case that really you know got my attention and happened here in arizona was uh the jody arias i remember that dude that was a big deal out here now i didn't live here at that time because i moved here in 09 and so i knew about that upon coming here oh you were moved here a year after it happened yeah it was it was around that time so it uh
I mean,
she got sentenced in 2015,
too?
Yeah.
That long?
Think about that,
dude.
That's a long time.
Yeah.
So what led you to Jodi?
How did you end up here?
In my opinion,
I think the mental health is one.
Okay.
Someone who is,
you know,
obviously good looking.
They come in,
they're hypersexual,
you know.
To me,
I recognize that's a sign of bipolar.
And,
you know,
somebody that has the looks,
you mix.
The
the sex in it,
and then the heinous crime,
and then the topping is the religion.
So those are like the four aspects that really make a crime,
at least the four pillars that make a crime.
one,
stand out,
but also get that media attention,
right?
Like the
Menendez brothers.
And to Jared's point,
the Lori Vallow.
Lori Vallow was a,
she was a baddie,
dog.
I mean,
she don't look like that now in the court system,
but back in the day,
she was an attractive woman.
I mean,
look at it.
Yeah.
Religion,
right?
You look at
Manson. You know,
he was some sort of cult,
but those are also called religions,
right?
Jim Jones,
you know,
with drinking the juice.
You also have the UFO cult slash religion with uh
Bonnie Nettles and
Heaven's Gate.
That's when they all,
it was a group of them that died,
right?
Well,
that's Jim Jones.
That was Jim
Jones. This Alien Cult was different,
though.
Why is that?
It is.
It's so grim,
but yeah,
we have this fascination.
I mean,
it's the same thing.
I think it's the same.
I think it taps into a different part of,
and probably an even more raw one,
because it's
It's like people why do people like jumping out of airplanes for some or why do people like roller coasters it's like you get or why do you like action movies you can get that thrill without engaging in it yeah and there is that darkness like the propensity to kill it
It exists.
We're human beings and we have the ability to defend ourselves.
So the ability to take a life,
but knowing that it's extreme,
I think people enjoy that little dance with it.
But then you tie in,
potentially,
your brain's telling you you're attracted to this person.
religion in there think about think about how people once the crime is committed and they're they're sentenced think about all the fans and the letters and stuff that guys get married in prison when you look at that case specifically that was 10 years ago like i said when the conviction but the murder happened in 2008 but
that's right around the time where like court tv and in the viewership.
People wanting to see this really
really took off.
You know,
once again,
I was trying to find,
well,
which case would it have been to where producers and television studios were like,
hey,
this could be something for the future.
And the Jodi Arias case is the one that sticks out the most.
You know what I mean?
And being that,
you know,
the Jodi Arias trial happened here,
at the time,
I didn't realize it,
but I...
I know,
knew,
and still know some very important figures that were involved in that case,
like Sheriff Joe.
Wow.
He,
you know,
he was the one that took over and,
brought her into the Maricopa County Jails.
And I went out to his office to sit down and just talk with him.
And you'll see what files that he has and information that he still has on that case.
One,
he's old,
but,
you know,
got to keep him remembered.
That was 2008,
2015.
That was a while ago.
Is he in his 80s now?
He's actually,
Sheriff Joe is like 92,
93.
Whoa.
He's up there.
Yeah.
And,
you know,
surprisingly,
like I said,
I personally know him.
So being able to go and sit down and talk with him,
he looks very good for his age.
Fountain Hills will do that to you.
Fountain Hills will definitely do that to him.
You'll probably live it all right in the mountains.
Yeah.
But,
you know,
now that he's not in law enforcement anymore and having to deal with these high profile.
cases and celebrities and probably good for the blood pressure absolutely yeah but you know talking about this case with him in specific um i quickly learned you know why he took over the case and um you know he he did answer some of the questions indirectly
or sometimes even off camera but uh one of the questions you know that i had was you know did you take over this case to specifically let her hang herself in those interviews because
That information can be used against you at a later time.
And with that aspect in thinking of her mental illness,
going against the advice of your lawyers to sit there and just talk on camera freely.
Clearly,
that was a sign that she was mentally unstable.
Zero out of ten lawyers recommend that.
Yeah.
Particularly when it pertains to a murder trial.
I was sheriff for 24 years.
Actually the longest in the history of the Republic of the Counties.
So I saw a lot of things in 24 years.
As the elected sheriff,
you know,
I was head of the
DEA, Dragon Force,
and all over the world.
It was a different type of operation than being the elected sheriff.
Now,
I really didn't do this for politics,
but in a way,
in a way,
every politician.
If they're smart,
go a little further than like a chief of police and all that,
that's really a bureaucrat.
So that's not why I took a special interest in areas,
because I've taken over other cases that are very controversial.
They're even more so than areas.
And when I say taken over...
I don't go around knocking the doors in or interviewing someone,
but I take control,
management control.
So this was one of the cases that I had an interest in.
Not because it was high profile,
although that's one of the reasons,
but it was a challenge.
And she was in my jail.
She had to eat the food and do everything that everybody else did.
Now she thought she was a prima donna,
that she should be treated differently.
Well,
I'm an equal opportunity incarcerator.
I treat everybody the same way.
Now,
there's a lot of media attention to this.
remember,
I didn't lock her up.
I wasn't the arresting agency.
My job was to make sure she's safe and secure in the jails I run.
And since I run the jails,
I make the decision what they eat.
You know,
it's talked that I feed them garbage.
it's true,
I feed the dogs that I had in jail better than her.
But she sort of knew how to manipulate,
even from the jail.
Manipulate.
Explain that.
What do you mean by manipulate?
Well,
she knows how to deal with the media.
And being a nice guy,
I would let the media come in and interview her.
I didn't have to let the media come to the cell block and interview her,
but I allowed that.
I had nothing to hide.
I let them interview any
M.A.
So she had that option,
although I did cut her off eventually.
And then another key figure that
I know,
his name is Darren Birch,
and he was the sergeant of Kronstock,
a silent witness over the Maricopa case.
County.
And,
you know,
he,
surprisingly,
he had some real ill feelings towards Jody Arias and even the case because he has to use the media to get his information out there,
you know,
and that case just took over everything,
the radio,
the news,
newspapers,
and he was not able to get his job done the entire time,
you know,
so a lot of stuff was happening on his end that,
he just wasn't able to push out there.
I'm retired Sergeant Darren Burch with the Phoenix Police Department.
Spent 30 years with the Phoenix Police Department and worked everything from patrol to detective.
Got promoted to sergeant,
then became a detective sergeant.
In 2008,
I became the Crime Stopper Sergeant for Maricopa County,
which includes Mesa,
Phoenix,
Scottsdale,
and so forth.
And Jodieras,
that crime occurred in June of 2008.
I very quickly learned that when a big crime like that occurs,
it takes up the news cycle.
And as a crime stopper sergeant,
wanting to affect the tips you need to get on the news.
There's other media you can get into,
but news is best.
It's visual.
It affects people.
And I learned very quickly from the media experts that there's four pillars that will get anything on the news,
and that's sex.
murder,
any type of religion,
and any kind of jealousy,
where you have that passion,
ugly passion,
but it's still passion.
And Jody Arias'
case had all four.
It really did.
So it wasn't a shock to me when I realized all my media contacts were trying desperately to be able to show the Jody Arias trial live.
And that was huge.
The courts didn't want it.
The actual presiding judge of that trial did
did not want a camera in their courtroom.
But the media was able to push it all the way to the higher courts,
and the higher courts allowed it.
It's going to the news cycle,
and again,
not just for a month,
which is a long jury trial.
She testified for a month.
There was so much testimony going on,
so much evidence that that trial lasted.
a long time.
And so as the crime stopper sergeant,
when I wanted to put out information about crimes I need help with,
I couldn't do it because it took over.
It was a circus.
It was almost like,
it's almost like sharks feeding this frenzy.
The courts,
the attorneys were always on the news.
It just took up all the oxygen in the room.
So I couldn't even present my cases during that timeframe.
So I absolutely.
I despised Jodi Arias.
That's why when the defense attorney said,
I'm not practicing law anymore,
and he literally gave up his law license and wrote the book,
Surviving Jodi Arias,
I understood what he meant because she affected so many people in the judicial system.
Crime stoppers,
cops,
it took all the oxygen in the room when you talk about the media as being a source of good.
to help solicit tips in the community.
I didn't have that availability.
I think right off the bat too,
one of the things that stands out to me,
and I'm sure someone will hear this and be in the comments,
so I won't speak definitely here,
but in general,
one of the few cases that the case is named after the killer.
You know what I mean?
It's,
it's,
I remember a big one for me growing up.
So honestly,
Jodi Arias was probably the second biggest one that was like something on my radar.
Lacey Peterson,
because I was in California at the time.
You know,
you think about things like that,
and it's the victim.
This is the sweet thing.
And it's not like the guy,
I mean,
yeah,
he wasn't an Abercrombie model,
but he was a good-looking,
you know,
like,
just normal-looking dude.
Like,
he would easily have been like,
oh,
my God,
that guy got killed.
You would have felt bad for him,
but it went with Jody,
and I think it goes a little bit back to media and what's going to sell.
You don't get that many attractive lady killers.
You don't get that.
And they ran with it,
it sounds like.
It became a circus.
When you have somebody like Jodi Arias,
who is now testifying on her own behalf,
and she spends an unprecedented 18 days on the witness stand,
18 days.
And keep in mind,
in trial,
you really just have trials from Monday.
to Thursday.
Friday is a admin day,
so you have four days a week of trial.
So that makes it,
she was there for over a month talking about how it was everyone else's fault.
She was throwing down everybody,
her parents,
her friends.
It was everyone else's fault and especially the victim.
It was the ultimate victim bashing that she began.
Talked about him being a pedophile,
how he hurt her,
how he was all these horrible things.
It backfired on her.
It didn't work,
but what it did do,
it made her an instant celebrity because everyone,
you could go anywhere in the nation at that time,
and maybe even today,
and ask,
who is Jodi Arias?
And they'll know.
Nine out of 10 people will know who Jodi Arias is.
But if you ask people who
Travis Alexander is,
they won't know.
And sadly,
Travis was born and raised in Riverside and was buried there because of her,
and they won't even know his name.
You can look back and see that there were definitely triggers.
And one of the things that was definitely overlooked in this case was the camera,
the aspect of the camera.
As she was doing the act?
Yes.
You mean?
Yeah,
yes.
The one that sticks in my head is that there's a picture of him that she took in...
when he was in the shower.
Right before it happened.
Oh,
that was the one right before.
Yes.
Literally right before she.
Oh,
did she have,
was she armed in that one?
Yes.
Wait,
did I miss that?
Dude,
she shot him in the head.
I thought she was toying with him before that.
She took the pictures before she.
Yes.
So there's that picture where he's standing.
Yeah.
And then after that,
there's a picture where he's laying in a puddle of blood.
That I remember.
Okay.
I forgot it was right before that.
But it was just like,
even if he didn't know it was coming,
like just dead inside.
Like he was just,
you can see it in his eyes.
He was.
He was broken dealing with that.
She was a photographer.
There was a camera involved during the murder.
Yeah.
There was cameras involved afterwards.
That's an interesting element.
Yeah,
the camera's definitely a key factor.
The underline of this case is the camera.
Number one,
what was said that caused you to snap?
When you look at the crime itself,
Clearly she's in a manic episode.
She's operating off of impulses.
The voices are telling her what to do.
Look at how horrific it is,
but also that's not planned.
Those aren't planned actions.
She's acting off of impulses.
It almost feels like she went undiagnosed because even during the trial,
I think there was a psychotherapist.
and a couple psychologists,
and they all gave different diagnoses.
But of some behavioral health issue.
Some of the ones that were for the prosecution talked a lot about the PTSD aspect.
The ones for the defense talked about an actual issue with her in regards to her ability to know right or wrong.
So there's all these different type of diagnoses that occurred during even the pre-trial phase in terms of the psychiatrist.
interested.
and folks with a lot of initials after names.
But it was clear that she had some type of issue.
Again,
just the idea that she would go against her attorney's advice and keep talking,
keep hanging herself.
And to her own detriment,
she kept doing this.
Just screams there's something wrong with this young lady.
Not to the point that she doesn't understand right or wrong.
Not to the point where she doesn't understand what she did was a crime.
But to the point where...
She has something going on upstairs that isn't right.
She went over there the night before,
stayed the night.
Yeah.
And for me...
Weren't they broken up at the time?
No,
no.
They had gone back to...
Well,
the relationship was...
Back and forth.
It was...
Yeah.
Okay.
Plus,
she lived in another state.
So,
she didn't live here.
If I'm not mistaken,
she lived in either Utah or California.
Okay.
it was in california that's right so she was driving back and forth that's why she had the gas can because if i think she was that route yeah she was taking a route so she was like the the actual trip that she took and there's gas receipts but i don't think she knew that the rental car they were able to keep track of the miles and locations that's what yes so
they when she turned the rental car in she went to like vegas california all these different places before she had put in like 2,800 miles.
on the car before she turned it in.
So what we were looking at,
especially talking with Darren,
was obviously,
you know,
she planned on killing him.
But did she plan on killing him that day in specific?
Because when a woman disconnects,
she's not going to come to your house the night before,
sleep with you and then kill you the next day.
If she snapped,
truly snapped.
It would be in the moment.
Communication between Jodi and Travis became fraught with tension.
What may have seemed like typical relationship struggles turned into a battleground of emotions.
Jodi's manic energy pushed her to extremes,
perceiving any rejection as a personal attack.
In the days before the fatal encounter,
Jodi's mental state deteriorated.
The lines between love and rage blurred,
culminating in a moment filled with desperation and chaos.
Thoughts raced through her mind,
leading to her act without regard for potential consequences.
In the moments leading up to the tragic event,
her emotions likely oscillated.
between love and rage culminating in a desperate act born of turmoil the frenzied energy of her manic episode may have propelled her towards an irreversible decision so
she had a knife she had the gun she was there the night before so she might have been planning this but when you look at
the actual killing itself keep in mind he's in the shower she takes a picture of defenseless listen i'm just gonna say right now completely defenseless come to this house 99 of the time it's gonna end badly for you if you're gonna catch me lacking post coitus in the shower i'm toast dude that straps across the room i'm not in that mindset i mean just truly you're drained yeah that's it you're done you're so if it was if it was planned defense grades down dude she drained him
And,
you know,
that's why she went there,
to literally drain him of his energy.
Damn.
Jeez.
I didn't even think about it.
Basically,
he was one of those guys where he was,
like,
came off as a player.
He's like,
I'm Mormon.
Yeah,
he's like,
I'm Mormon.
You know,
I'm trying to save myself till marriage.
Basically,
he kind of finessed that situation.
She started basically becoming,
like,
in love with him,
but he would always keep her at a distance.
She transferred to being a Mormon.
She moved out there to where she converted.
She converted to Mormon.
Yes.
He actually baptized her.
There's pictures.
Yeah,
he baptized her personally.
Okay,
listen.
I get why she snapped.
He broke it off and was like,
basically,
this isn't working out.
She had already moved there.
So he started seeing somebody else.
She would like stalk and basically she sent the girlfriend at the time like a crazy email.
Basically,
like you're going to you're going to have to go through with the choices of the things that you're going through.
Thank you.
the murder itself and how it happened um you know you stab somebody
27 times and shoot them well oh she sliced his throat at some point they're stabbed and then they're slicing yeah she stabbed him shot him in the head and then sliced him ear to ear when
you slice a grown when you're a woman you slice a grown man ear to ear
That's vengeance.
That's not...
Was it...
okay...
That's not accidental.
So part of me feels like this was premeditated,
but there's one specific type of mental state that happens.
I feel like in a lot of murders,
I feel like I personally feel like in the OJ case this happened.
There's a thing called dissociative,
disassociative amnesia,
meaning when a traumatic event happens,
there's an unknown period of time where you know your body basically shuts that part off of part of your brain and forgets it.
So everything that...
She probably did was very premeditated,
driving around and all those things that seemed like a premeditated murder.
But her story of every time that she kept getting interviewed,
her story would change is because those memories would be very blurry.
And she couldn't figure out a perfect way to lie.
But she also couldn't find a perfect way to tell the truth because she didn't remember any of those things.
I think it evokes a whole OJ Simpson scenario where it was.
it was a heinous crime and it was by and anytime you have something like that where you have i hate to use the word overkill but you have like that many staff rooms some of them were life threatening in and of themselves and then the overkill of a gunshot to the forehead which is probably post-mortem that
screams somebody within your inner circle boyfriend girlfriend husband wife.
jilted lover.
It just screams of that.
So
Jody was really the first suspect that police would even look at.
And then you add the 911 call.
The 911 call when he didn't show up for a teleconference meeting and then his friends got worried.
They went to his home.
They were able to get a key to get into his bedroom and they found him.
When they called 911,
one of the excited utterances was,
oh my God,
Jody.
They even threw her down then.
So it was clear.
She was the suspect.
Even though she said she was in Mesa,
it was proven instantly she was.
It was a bad,
bad lie.
It could be disproved instantly.
So it was two years later before she finally even admitted she murdered him.
But even then,
she had to say in her mind,
not taking responsibility,
not owning it,
saying that it was self-defense.
She was charged with murder,
and she was in there.
All the time.
Then she eventually went to the prison because we only hold people in our jail system.
They could do their time there.
Like the tents,
they're all convicted.
...with non-convicted people in the tents.
That's why she was never in the tents,
because she wasn't convicted,
number one.
And number two,
once you're convicted on a felony,
you leave the jail and go to the state prison.
But while she was in the jail,
for long periods of time,
until you go to court,
get sentenced,
you know,
and all that,
they stayed with me.
So
I do know a lot of the inmates kind of want to plead guilty to get out of the jail.
They hate the jail so much that they'd rather go to prison because you eat pretty good in the state prison.
This is a jail.
So she had access,
in a way,
to our commissary.
Now,
the inmates have a chance to buy a chocolate bar.
at the commissary that we have if they don't like the food.
So I'm sure she took advantage of that.
And
I almost believe she became like a jailhouse hero because all the inmates have ways to see what's going on.
Not through TV.
I think she got mad because the only TV
I showed.
was the weather channel and the food channel.
I don't give them access,
so she couldn't be seeing herself.
Probably made her very angry on the interviews.
So she's interviewed by TV,
hoping to see it,
but she has a problem because I don't show the regular TV in the jail.
So,
but she,
I would have to call her a,
you know,
a good inmate in that sense,
not because of the crime.
But she knew how far,
she liked to exercise,
she's exercising and all that.
And she probably had a reputation of being the queen of the cell area.
And so.
I put up with her,
but then I cut her off.
No more interviews.
Something happened.
It was going too far with her.
So I cut her off.
That made big news.
In your opinion,
you know,
obviously we know she did the crime,
but in your opinion,
what do you think went wrong that night between her and Travis?
Well,
it wasn't my case.
I didn't investigate that case.
So I can't talk too much about the details.
The big part is how I treated her in my jails that I run.
But,
you know,
I have ideas.
I know what happened.
You know,
media made a big,
big story over this.
We have other vicious people too,
but for some reason she struck a chord.
Maybe being a woman,
she was a good looking and got involved in this situation.
The altercation,
whatever you want to call it.
So even that part was kind of extraordinary for the media to pursue.
Just the murder itself,
and so on,
not what happened in the jail.
But she was able to try to manipulate the jail system.
Keep in mind that as the Crime Stopper Sergeant,
it doesn't matter where in the country or the world for that matter,
your job is to get a message to the public and use these different platforms like the news agencies,
TV,
radio,
and so forth.
So you learn very quickly what the media wants.
The problem is that when you have something like Judy Arias,
where you have this horrific crime,
that in itself is a media darling.
You got a victim that was stabbed.
Sliced over 27 times.
He had his carotid ripped.
He had his trachea ripped.
He was shot in the head after all this,
post-mortem.
So it was a heinous crime.
So that in and of itself rises to a level of media attention.
It really does.
But when you add arguably an attractive figure like Jodi Arias,
whether you think she's attractive or not,
there are people out there that do.
And you have sex between her and the victim,
and it's wild sex.
And then you have religion.
He baptized her like a month after they met,
before they got intimate.
And then when they got intimate,
they got crazy with the cameras.
One of the big items of evidence was the camera that he was taking pictures,
or she was taking pictures,
we don't know,
of their sexual encounter.
hours before she killed him.
In fact,
one of the pictures was of him bleeding profusely to what we really couldn't see his face on the shower floor.
What is your theory on why she did what she did in that moment?
Yeah,
the prosecution tried to lay out the framework that this was planned,
premeditated,
thought out to the nth degree.
And that could be true.
The problem I have with that is their sexual relation prior to the crime.
To me,
that screamed not a planned event for that moment.
Doesn't mean she wasn't thinking about maybe killing him,
maybe so angry,
because they had a very rocky relationship by all accounts,
whether you talk to her friends or you talk to his friends.
They had a rocky relationship.
They were on the outs.
It was long.
distance.
He had other girlfriends on the side and there was always this tumultuous relationship.
And what really hit me with her is sometimes people say things and it's a Floridian slip.
And her defense,
she said that he was angry because she broke his camera,
that she dropped it in the shower and it broke.
So maybe the camera was an element.
of that snap but maybe or most definitely not per her story it wasn't because he became angry but maybe he was doing some filming and she felt dissed and now you're breaking up with me and there's this camera with these these
evidence of my sexual escapades so it was like insult on injury and that could have made her snap went to the kitchen was angry and then sees a knife and then
that moment she goes into killer mode it's just interesting how jody arias's name like really took over the case uh she took over i mean when you really look at it she was she was really the mastermind like this girl was not stupid at all you
know what i mean like she was able to commit a crime and one thing that i noticed like the looks didn't really appear you
Like she didn't come off as a girl that knew she was beautiful prior to the murder.
Kind of naive.
Right.
Because you know how some of the girls are when they know they look good.
If you go to Old Town Scottsdale,
you'll see the ones that know what they look like.
She meets a nice LDS guy.
Let's be real.
Jodi in Scottsdale and living in that type of Tempe.
Yep.
You put it together.
You're like,
yeah,
she didn't really know about the looks until after.
Yeah,
she would have been kind of an average Joe.
Right?
Maybe so.
Yeah.
But it wasn't until she got arrested.
You know,
the photos.
Yeah.
Your mug shots are
are so sensationalized nowadays people are like i want to bail this girl out or the guy that with the green eyes the tattoos you know yes i remember that guy yes he got a modeling deal after that right so it's like if you look at it we really look yes we can look at oj and and that was one of the ones where it was you know we actually had the news but
where that shift where the news was starting to close out in podcasts and social media and all that stuff
it it the jody areas case sticks out yeah by far okay go ahead go ahead okay do you uh you mentioned like okay so do you feel like the cameras were a bit of a trigger do you think and we said maybe bipolar multiple personality disorder whatever that was
Do you think there's an element of like narcissism or psychopathy there?
And then she was someone who late in life maybe discovers that,
oh,
I have looks here.
Like she starts hearing things like,
oh,
people are,
you're going through this thing,
but people are saying you're good looking or something when mugshot.
comes out and that she starts hearing coverage of it do you think that's like what you were maybe joe recognized is like oh there's an element of that here and if i if i you know that's gasoline and basically and there once there's some spark so
the the the common factor between joe and joe and jody is the cameras they love cameras you know joe joe sheriff joe he he loves cameras right So it was...
it was an opportunity and I hate to use the word opportunity,
but it was an opportunity for him to take a high profile case.
But also it doesn't take long,
especially as guys to know when somebody's mental state is off,
especially a female.
This is true.
So,
you know,
it's,
it's sitting there,
you know,
probably the guards and everybody,
and even the inmates,
this,
this she's a little off a rocker.
They gave each other the nod.
Yep.
And then,
you know,
she wants interviews,
cameras,
all of that stuff has to be approved by Sheriff Joe.
You know,
sitting down to talk to him,
I was like,
oh,
wow,
a lot of those interviews that took place happened in your jail.
If you know she's unstable,
it's going to turn into a high profile case.
The murder happened in 08.
She wasn't convicted until 2015.
That's seven years later.
Right.
And then on top of that,
that's seven years of publicity.
you know on top of the other high profile cases that's when it was sb 49 what was that what was going on at that time what was that law that sheriff joe implemented was that all the it was sb something it was like sb intensive no no it was it was when he was pulling people over you remember that it was like sb 49 or sb i don't remember the exact there's some law but that was around that time yes correct
it was the arizona version of that and so to your point it just clicked in my head that
Yeah,
that was Sheriff Joe's time.
He was always on the news and you were always seeing him constantly.
And you got to look at it like the sheriff is really a political position,
right?
You're elected.
It's not like the Westerns anymore.
He's not out there.
He's not the best gunslinger in town.
Exactly.
And not only that,
he was sheriff for like 24,
25 years.
I mean,
a long,
that's almost three decades.
I dealt with her and really had no problem.
She was sort of a...
A good inmate,
in that sense.
Caused some problems.
I think the weight of the evidence finally sunk in.
I really do.
I think it was beyond the pale that she could think that she could get away with this crime with all the evidence against her.
So in her mind,
she thought,
you know what?
I'm a victim.
Regardless of the viciousness of the attack,
regardless of the...
premeditated aspect of the gas can,
the car,
the fake burglary reports that she could get a gun.
All that leads to premeditated.
It really does.
But I think when she looked at the evidence,
at some point,
I don't know how smart she is.
I know she didn't finish high school,
but that doesn't necessarily mean she's illiterate.
She's gifted,
clearly.
She can sing,
She can draw,
she can paint,
very.
artistic young lady.
But
I don't know how her cognitive functioning could have looked at that case and thought,
I need to shut the hell up and let my defense attorney represent me.
Instead,
she just had this overwhelming need for attention.
She just did.
And it's possible,
and again,
you'd have to ask a psychiatrist,
but sometimes if you tell a lie long enough,
you start to believe it.
So did she try to convince herself?
Or did she convince herself?
You know,
by allowing her to,
you know,
really stick a camera in her face and just let her go,
I think people knew.
I'm pretty confident.
Confident that they knew and they just let it go.
You know,
if we take the cameras out of her life,
we take the cameras out of the jail cells.
Keep in mind,
she also sang that song.
I don't know if you heard that.
The old Holy Night song.
And that like it is very disturbing.
It almost sounds like a confession.
And she maybe like four months prior,
she actually changed her story like a third or fourth time and said.
you know what she did self-defense and all that stuff but the timing the song itself very creepy see i had a program remember uh it made idol or i think uh american american
i think uh fox did uh which by the way fox doesn't talk to me anymore i'm not going to mention some guy that i investigated for this
picture is right up there.
So,
inmate,
I said,
I'm going to do inmate idol.
It's good for the inmates.
They have something to do.
They can start singing and try to win.
I forgot what the reward was.
Maybe it was steak instead of bologna.
I don't know.
There's some reward.
So then
Cooper, he's a great.
He's a nice guy,
Alice Cooper.
I said,
hey,
I need a judge.
Will you help me?
Oh,
yeah,
sure.
So
I used him as a judge,
an inmate idol,
me and him.
We decide which inmate is going to not win,
the fix isn't in.
But she just happened to win.
So we went through the whole system,
preliminary.
You know,
also eliminate some of the people that can't even talk in the jail,
forget singing.
So we had a final deal,
and she gets up there.
She did a pretty good job.
In December of 2010,
in the Maricopa County Jail,
ran by former sheriff Joe Arpaio,
a contest took place in the form of American Idol called
Inmate Idol.
Jody beat out 50 other inmates to win this competition and with permission from Joe Arpaio,
here's a video of the song that she sang.
O holy night,
the stars are brightly shining,
It is the night of our dear Savior's birth.
Long lay the world in sin and error pining,
Till He appeared and the soul felt its worth.
A thrill of hope,
the weary world rejoices,
for yonder breaks a new and glorious morn.
Fall on your knees,
oh hear the angel voices,
oh night divine.
When
Christ was born,
oh,
na diva,
na diva.
Now,
she probably had a lot of time to sing.
She's,
you know,
she's,
I'm not going to call her an informer,
you know,
an informer to sing,
to confess and all that.
So she knew how to do it.
And she made something out of herself in a bad way.
You know,
when you start chopping somebody's head off or whatever,
that's not nice.
But she took advantage of that.
So
I played along with her.
She was high profile.
A lot of media wanted to talk to her.
I said,
okay.
Now I let the media talk to a lot of people.
Now this one,
as I say,
had a way to get the story out.
But I think I cut her off.
As time went on,
it was getting too,
too complicated how she would use the interview.
And don't forget,
she was through a court system,
facing a death penalty and all that.
But I did allow people to talk to her.
The most important thing in a jury trial is getting the jury to understand the crime scene.
as it relates to the evidence,
but also to the investigators.
For example,
when that 911 call came out and patrol is responding,
this is a patrol response,
and they get there,
they're looking at this horrendous,
bloody scene that is not just in the shower,
but now they have a bloody palm print on the wall,
and now they're going to follow any kind of blood trail because he was fighting for his life.
and 27 stab wounds
27 areas for there to be bleeding and perfusive bleeding.
This is one of those horrific scenes that's right out of the movies.
You're looking at all the intricate things to include cameras.
You're looking at,
and then you find a camera and a washing machine?
Well,
that goes right through forensics.
So this is a crime scene that gave up so much evidence.
Jody,
again,
is suspect number one.
And that's based on a crime scene that just screamed her name.
And I could be wrong on this,
but I think that if she went into delete mode,
not only was the crime on there,
but I think she found something on that camera that she wasn't expecting.
Could be.
Very,
very possible.
As she's going through the camera,
she could find another girl.
Absolutely a possibility.
But to our point,
I think the camera is the key.
I think the camera is key because she used it as a defense mechanism.
Like he was angry because I dropped it.
And so the camera was on her mind.
Yeah,
because to the prosecution's credit,
they talked a lot about the rental vehicle and the gas can so that she could hide her travel.
She had a gas can that she would fill up the vehicle so there was no,
you know,
documentation of that trip going from...
gas station to gas station.
So it makes sense that it was planned.
I just don't know if it was planned.
Like maybe this wasn't the only trip she took with a gas can.
Maybe there was other times she visited him because she clearly would visit him.
And there's times where he would visit her.
They had this long distance relationship,
booty calls,
if you will.
And it's real possible that this was just one of many type of trips where she had it in the back of her mind.
She had the gun.
She would fake the travel where no one would know,
she thought.
So this may not have been her first foray in this belief that she might kill him.
That was another part of the trial too,
right?
It was like they wanted the death penalty.
The jury,
I guess,
voted against it because in the state of Arizona,
there's still the death penalty,
right?
You can still die.
Pretty conflicted on it though.
I think the panel was...
Is that what it is?
Yeah.
So there was...
There's two different situations that happened.
I think one was a...
Hung jury.
And then one of them was,
I don't remember,
I don't know,
remember the legal term,
but basically it was a claim to as a mistrial.
Yep.
And that's where the Juan Martinez information where he leaked,
well,
he didn't leak,
he was telling a blogger inside information.
And he was,
I don't know exactly what it,
but when you go to court where you're going to be disbarred.
But both attorneys use the media to their advantage.
Juan Martinez,
which was a prosecutor.
Every day,
practically,
he would stop and talk with the media about it.
He would talk about different things and trying to get the public on his side,
if you will.
And I tell you,
when she was announced guilty,
when the indictment came,
there was a crowd of cheers because of how disgusting she killed him.
She wanted the attention.
She wanted to convince people that she was innocent.
to a point where it was ridiculous.
And against her attorney's advice,
she could not help herself and kept wanting these interviews.
Not just before,
but during and even after,
she still kept doing these interviews.
And every one was potential for her to hang herself.
She couldn't help herself.
She loved the spotlight.
She loved what in her mind was fame without the fortune.
She loved the attention.
And
I don't know if she truly thought she could outlie herself in this situation because the evidence was so damning that there's not a...
in the world to include Kirk Nermey that's going to say,
oh yeah,
talk to the press.
No,
you don't talk.
It's rule number one.
She broke rule number one over and over again.
It's more telling of who she is than what the case was.
And then the other situation that Drew was talking about is one of the jurors said no to the death penalty.
And that juror actually was receiving
death threats after that so the the Jodi Arias case the
I mean there's just so much a fallout that was involved with that case I mean the lawyers both of them no longer practicing wow uh Travis Alexander and you know you got to keep in mind people know here
we say Jodi Arias but who did she kill
Exactly.
Other cases,
Gabby Patino,
I think it was,
you know,
like,
and Brian was,
I know it was Brian
Laundrie, I think.
So,
like,
I know the killer's name,
but it takes me a second.
Like,
that was the Gabby Patino case.
It was the Lacey Peterson.
And OK,
yeah,
the husband's name was Scott Peterson.
But it's like it was never.
I just recently I just finished the John Wayne Gacy doc on Netflix.
And that was one thing that Joe Berlinger,
who's done a lot of those doc documentaries.
It's like.
a lot of times they focus on the murderer versus the people who were murdered.
You know what's interesting?
When you look at,
and I talked about the fact that we don't know
Travis Alexander's name.
We know Jody Harris'
name.
But it's not that true about the attorneys.
Both attorneys had a lot of attention driven on them because they were part of this soap opera,
this live soap opera involving sex,
murder,
religion,
jealousy,
rage,
all these things.
They were part of that soap opera.
And
I know for a fact Juan Martinez,
the prosecutor,
got sucked into it.
No doubt.
I mean,
he got disbarred or he gave it up because of the accusations that he was giving inside information to a blogger,
real-time information during the trial.
That was the accusation.
He said he didn't do it,
but he ended up giving up his license so he wouldn't have to go to trial for that.
And then you look at
Kurt and Ermi,
you know,
you end up getting cancer.
Was that because of the stress?
Because stress does a lot to you.
And he had a lot of stress going on during that time period.
He had a client that wouldn't listen to him.
He had a client that would not shut up.
And he's doing everything legitimately in his powers as a defense attorney to protect her from herself and can't.
How frustrating is that?
To the point where he gave up his license.
Yep.
two attorneys.
The two attorneys no longer practice law.
She didn't only kill
Travis and figuratively kill his reputation.
I think she also killed those two attorneys,
figuratively speaking.
She killed her whatever she had.
Her life is gone.
Travis is gone.
Those attorneys are gone.
A lot of fallout.
There's a lot of fallout with her.
And again,
I'm not saying that their actions doesn't speak to who they are,
but they were put in a situation where she was really the person orchestrating everything.
If you think about it,
she wants to be understood.
You can't stop her.
You can give her all the great advice in the world,
but you can't stop her from talking.
And now she's talking,
talking.
She is a calamity.
She's a train wreck and she keeps talking.
And the pressures that occurred during this trial,
if you will,
it's a trial of the century,
that end up hurting more than just her.
It ended up hurting a lot of the people involved,
to include that jury.
We haven't even talked about the death threats that the jurors had.
You have the initial phase,
which they all found her guilty.
But during the sentencing trial to determine whether or not it was going to be a death sentence,
with the capital murder aspect.
You had one juror who did not want to go along with the other
11 and did not want her put to death.
And that juror had death threats.
That juror's information was leaked to the public,
and they had death threats against them.
I don't want to give away the gender or anything because I don't want to add to that.
But there's a lot of casualties,
a lot of people that were hurt by Jodi Ayers on top of the crime itself.
Just based on the trial.
Hey,
you got to give her credit for one thing.
Maybe if she was an honest gal,
maybe in there just for drunk driving,
maybe I would have hired her.
I hired her as my public relations officer.
So in lieu of that,
I dealt with her and really had no problem.
I don't think there's any elements you could change within the trial that would have precluded or negated the ultimate indictment.
Not at all.
The case was solid.
The evidence was solid.
She did it.
But there's things you could have done to limit the fallout.
First and foremost is not having a live camera in a murder trial with somebody that's such a narcissist that wants that attention and that will talk and just you don't know what you're going to get.
The center of attention,
it becoming a circus,
that added fuel to the fire that really burnt a lot of people involved in this case.
So I think
The end result of her being life in prison would never have changed,
regardless of any of the elements you could change to include the attention with the media.
But by not having a live streaming camera and such a debacle of a defendant,
she was her worst enemy,
but she was also an enemy of all of us.
Because if you witness that,
And again,
I never watched a single show.
I never watched a single.
I was hearing it,
not daily,
hourly from my contacts in the media.
They would tell me,
oh,
did you hear this?
Do you hear this?
You couldn't avoid it,
especially in my line of work.
You couldn't avoid it.
But by limiting that live stream,
by limiting the cameras,
that is a good thing.
And I just noticed maybe they've learned because in a lot of cases.
You don't have that same effect.
Now again,
court TV is everywhere.
You know,
there is that component out there,
that need for that sensationalizing entertainment.
Giving into it as entertainment.
Who are we hurting?
We're hurting,
yeah,
the defendant,
the prosecution,
defense,
but I think we're hurting ourselves too.
When she sang All Holy Night,
it's a complete difference.
That's the scared little girl that's realizing what she's done.
And that song almost feels like a confession,
but it's very unfortunate and it's sad.
Travis is no longer here.
She's in prison the rest of her life.
Knowing the signs that she was not mentally there,
reacting off of impulses,
the manipulation in the court,
everywhere with the media.
All the signs were there,
and she went undiagnosed,
probably her entire life,
probably still,
till this day.
Oh,
holy night,
the stars are brightly shining.
It is the night of our dear Savior's birth.
Long lay the world in sin and error pining,
till He appeared and the soul felt its worth.
A thrill of hope the weary world rejoices,
for yonder breaks a new and glorious morn.
Oh hear the angel voices,
oh night divine,
when Christ was born,
oh night divine.
I'm so surprised I didn't want to get it out.
Oh my God.
Which,
by the way,
Fox doesn't talk to me anymore.
I'm not going to mention some guy that I investigated,
but his picture is right up there.
Mental health was overlooked.
Yeah.
Really?
I did not know that.
Wow.
Especially on her team,
I could see that.
I mean,
that was...
You should have just gotten out of there.
Yeah,
and he...
Apparently,
he was...
He was leaking inside information.
Whoa.
To,
like,
a blogger or something like that.
You got to keep in mind,
when I say blogger,
that was the time.
Well,
that back then.
Yes.
Huge.
When you think about it,
it wasn't that long ago.
Jen
Yeah,
the new generation might not know what that is,
but we do.
TV radio was still like the most popular podcast.
We're literally just becoming a thing.
Literally.
just become nothing.
That's where we saw everything on TV.
That's kind of where we saw it.
And then there was very few limited resources of like sourcing to get information of stories like this unless it was like the Times,
any type of newspaper publication.
So this is,
I think people were more excited about this because it was at the right age group where people were really interested.
It was different for the OJ case where he's a celebrity figure.
He's a little bit older,
so more people that grew up with him.
That's why it was so worldwide,
like a nationwide thing.
This was like,
this is somebody that could be your next-door neighbor.
Like,
it happened.
She was a photographer.
There was a camera involved during the murder.
Yeah.
There was cameras involved afterwards.
That's an interesting element.
Yeah,
the camera's definitely a key factor.
The underline of this case.
Is the camera.
Yeah.
And that's why I asked that.
You remove the cameras,
I think we get a different Jody.
You know,
these lawyers might still be in place.
Even down to where we are at with crime TV.
You talked about court television and all this stuff.
The need and thirst,
especially in women,
with crime and murder.
It's fascinating to look or focus,
no pun intended,
on the camera as a continuous element of this crime.
Again,
we talked a lot about the camera that was in the washing,
right?
That was direct evidence,
linking evidence to her crime.
But she was a photographer.
And then you add the cameras in the courtroom.
And this camera just keeps,
it's almost like...
This iconic image that if you were to paint a picture of this,
you just have to paint a camera.
And it had elements within all this.